A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations, Series T FA329
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations, Series T
1932-1990
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller family
FA329
21.5 Cubic Feet 49 document boxes.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr. C Business Interests D Civic Interests E Cultural Interests F Economic Reform Interests G Educational Interests H Friends and Services I Homes J Housing Interests K Medical Interests L Real Estate M Maps and Memorabilia N Religious Interests O Rockefeller Boards P Welfare - General Files Q World Affairs R Welfare - Youth Files S Documents T Public Relations U Public Land Law Review Commission V Greenrock W Properties X Costume Collection Y Media Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include: FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
- Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations, 1932-1990; T
  - Press Releases, 1
    - Radio Broadcasts, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Carter Plantation, Virginia, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ramon Magsaysay Award Program, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Press Releases, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
    - Nelson A. Rockefeller Collection Opening at Museum of Primitive Art - Mexican Folk Art - Press Kit, 1969 May 21-August 31 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 20th Century Art from the Nelson A. Rockefeller Collection from the Museum of Modern Art, 1969 May 28-September 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Press Releases, 1970-1973 June (Box 2, Folder 10-17)
    - Press Releases, 1973 July-1974 March (Box 3, Folder 18-21)
    - Press Releases, 1974 April-August (Box 4, Folder 22-30)
    - Press Releases, 1974 September-1975 April (Box 5, Folder 31-43)
    - Press Releases, 1975 May-1979 January (Box 6, Folder 44-50)
    - Press Releases - Miscellaneous, 1970-1976 (Box 7, Folder 51-57)
    - Annual Report - Rockefeller Brothers Fund, 1956-1973 (Box 8, Folder 58)
    - Five Year Review and Annual Report - Rockefeller Foundation, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 59)
    - Annual Report - Rockefeller Family Fund, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 60)
    - News Summaries, 1962-1969 (Box 9, Folder 61-65)
    - News Summaries, 1970-1973 (Box 10, Folder 66-69)
    - News Summaries, 1974-1977 (Box 11, Folder 70-73)
    - News Summaries, 1978-1979 (Box 12, Folder 74-75)
  - News Summaries, 2
    - News Summaries, 1954-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - News Summaries, 1962-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4-7)
    - News Summaries, 1969-1973 (Box 3, Folder 8-11)
    - News Summaries, 1974-1976 (Box 4, Folder 12-17)
    - News Summaries, 1977-1980 (Box 5, Folder 15-18)
    - News Summaries, 1981-1985 (Box 6, Folder 19-24)
  - Magazine Articles, 3
    - Magazine Articles, 1889-1927 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
    - Magazine Articles, 1928-1937 (Box 2, Folder 8-12)
    - Magazine Articles, 1939-1949 (Box 3, Folder 13-18)
    - Magazine Articles, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 19-22)
    - Magazine Articles, 1952-1954 (Box 5, Folder 23-27)
    - Magazine Articles, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 28-31)
    - Magazine Articles, 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 32-35)
    - Magazine Articles, 1959-1961 June (Box 8, Folder 36-40)
    - Magazine Articles, 1961 July-1963 June (Box 9, Folder 41-44)
    - Magazine Articles, 1963 July-1965 April (Box 10, Folder 45-48)
    - Magazine Articles, 1965 May-1967 March (Box 11, Folder 49-52)
    - Magazine Articles, 1967 April-1968 (Box 12, Folder 53-58)
    - Magazine Articles, 1969-1972 April (Box 13, Folder 59-64)
    - Magazine Articles, 1972 May-December (Box 14, Folder 65-68)
    - Magazine Articles, 1973 (Box 15, Folder 69-74)
    - Magazine Articles, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 75-79)
    - Magazine Articles, 1975 January-June (Box 17, Folder 80-83)
    - Magazine Articles, 1975 July-1976 June (Box 18, Folder 84-90)
    - Magazine Articles, 1976 July-1977 (Box 19, Folder 91-94)
    - Magazine Articles, 1978 (Box 20, Folder 95-103)
    - Magazine Articles, 1979 (Box 21, Folder 104-108)
    - Magazine Articles, 1980-1981 (Box 22, Folder 109-114)
    - Magazine Articles, 1982 (Box 23, Folder 115-119)
    - Magazine Articles, 1983-1985 (Box 24, Folder 120-123)
    - Magazine Articles, 1986-1990 (Box 25, Folder 124-130)
  - Speeches, 4
    - David Rockefeller Speeches, 1954, 1963, 1965-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1-11)
    - David Rockefeller Speeches, 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 12-16)
    - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Speeches, 1956, 1957, 1964, 1966-1973 (Box 3, Folder 17-26)
    - Laurance S. Rockefeller Speeches, 1959-1973, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 27-33)
    - Nelson A. Rockefeller Speeches, 1932-1949, 1951-1958, 1961-1976 (Box 5, Folder 34-40)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller Speeches, 1958-1964, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Paul Sherbert - Asia Society Speech, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - John D. Rockefeller IV (Jay) Speeches, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Jeannette E. Rockefeller Speeches, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Steven C. Rockefeller Speeches, 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Rodman Rockefeller, 1964-1972 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Mary French Rockefeller, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 47)